Guide to the Stanford University, Academic Council, Advisory Board Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Academic Council, Advisory Board records
1904-1975
1904-1948
SC0665
Stanford University. Academic Council. Advisory Board.
6.5 Linear feet
Minutes, memoranda, correspondence, reports, and other miscellaneous documents pertaining largely to faculty appointments and promotions in the university, including the Medical School, Law School, School of Education, Hopkins Marine Station, and the Graduate School of Business. Other issues the Board considered include academic organization and structures, policies regarding students (including the welfare of women students 1904-05), retirement and pension issues, and sabbatical leaves.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Advisory Board advises the President on recommendations for academic appointments, promotions, and dismissals; for the creation of new departments; for the abolition of departments; and any other matter that the President may choose to refer to it.
Description of the Collection
Minutes, memoranda, correspondence, reports, and other miscellaneous documents pertaining largely to faculty appointments and promotions in the university, including the Medical School, Law School, School of Education, Hopkins Marine Station, and the Graduate School of Business. Other issues the Board considered include academic organization and structures, policies regarding students (including the welfare of women students 1904-05), retirement and pension issues, and sabbatical leaves.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Academic Council. Advisory Board.; Women college students--California--Stanford.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - 1904 May – August (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Of note: recommendations for Dr. W. F. Durand, procedures on students delinquent in scholarship, salary guidelines, consolidation of departments
  - 1904 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Of note: consolidation of departments, letters re Jean du Buy
  - 1904 September – replies to Dr. Jordan's circular letter regarding salaries, etc. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    0
  - 1904 October – December (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Of note: report on art department by A. B. Clark, statement on new professorships needed, salaries, social policies for women students, recommendations for Harris J. Ryan and Henry W. Ballantine
  - 1905 January – February (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Of note: number of women students and their welfare, appointment of Julius Hanna as stenographic assistant
  - 1905 March – April (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Of note: formation of political science department, recommendations for Austin Flint Rogers and Payson J. Treat. [There are no papers relating to the Goebel case.]
  - 1905 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Of note: procedures for removal of faculty, recommendations for C. H. Huberich and Elmer R. Drew, formation of political science department
  - 1905 July – August (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Of note: recommendations for Leon P. Lewis and Henry David Gray
  - 1905 September – October (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Of note: recommendations for John E. Goodwin, committees for control of athletic grounds
  - 1905 November – December (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Of note: creation of new departments, report on work of the Board for 1904/05
  - 1906 January (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Of note: Carnegie Pension Fund, recommendations for A. A. Young and E. W. Kemmerer, possible offer to Frederick Jackson Turner in History Department
  - 1906 February (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Of note: recommendations for A. A. Young
  - 1906 March – April (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Of note: letter from Jordan on limiting numbers of students admitted and raising standards, earthquake notice of April 19, Jordan's nomination of Thorstein B. Veblen
  - 1906 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Of note: recommendations for John Crawford, response to Jordan's letter on limiting admissions, letter from E. P. Cubberley on work of School of Education in regard to certifying teachers, transfer of Cooper Medical College to Stanford
  - 1906 June – August (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Of note: recommendations for Frederick A. Manchester, Carnegie Pension Fund
  - 1906 September – October (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Of note: junior college concept, possibility of tuition charges, report on work of the board in 1905/06, retirement rules for faculty
  - 1906 December (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Of note: recommendations for James M. Motley, Theodore W. Koch, George H. Sabine, Theodore De Laguna, and Henry W. Stuart
  - 1907 January (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Of note: Law School appointments, appointment of university librarian, recommendations for Sidney Dean Townley
  - 1907 February (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Of note: appointment of university librarian, recommendations for Frederick C. Woodward and D. O. McGovney, regulations for granting sabbatical leave
  - 1907 March (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Of note: student fees, recommendation for Prof. Suzzallo and A. L. Guerard
  - 1907 April – July (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1907 August – September (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Of note: military science courses and recommendations for Capt. U. G. McAlexander, regulations for leave of absence
  - 1907 October – December (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Of note: student fees, rules for sabbatical leave
  - 1908 January (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Of note: recommendations for Mrs. Evelyn Wight Allan (Dean of Women)
  - 1908 February – March (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Of note: recommendations for Percy A. Martin, possible appointment of a Dean of Men, recommendation for Dr. Ram to teach class in Hebrew
  - 1908 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Of note: transfer of Medical School and Medical School faculty
  - 1908 May – June (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Of note: instruction in music courses
  - 1908 August – September (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Of note: recommendation of Herbert F. Coolidge as Secretary to the Committee on Student Affairs and the issue of student discipline, nomination of Herbert C. Hoover as lecturer in mining
  - 1908 October - November (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Of note: Jordan on desirability of Stanford representation at scholarly meetings, making department of law a graduate professional school
  - 1908 December (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Of note: junior college issue, recommendations for W. H. Lewis, A. W. Meyer, Herbert E. Bolton, and Thomas A. Clark
  - 1909 January (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Of note: recommendations for Thomas A. Clark and Edward B. Krehbiel, separation of the department of geology and mining
  - 1909 February – April (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1909 May – July (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Of note: restoring title "Secretary of the University" for G. A. Clark, recommendation and appointment for Robert E. Pellissier
  - 1909 August – September (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Of note: proposal for appointing Dr. Hersch Ram instructor in Semitic Languages (with funding from Rabbi Jacob Nieto)
  - 1909 October – December (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Of note: abolishing associate professorship in Greek
  - 1910 January – February (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Of note: status of Prof. H. W. Rolfe, retirement of Prof. M. B. Anderson,
  - 1910 March – April (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Of note: recommendation of Aurelio Macedonio Espinoso
  - 1910 May – August (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1910 September (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1910 October – December (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1911 January – February (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1911 March (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Of note: recommendations for E. E. Robinson, including medical professors in Academic Council
  - 1911 April – May (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Of note: recommendation and appointment of Robert E. Pellissier
  - 1911 June – July (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Of note: recommendations for Dr. Thomas Addis
  - 1911 August – September (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1911 October – December (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Of note: recommendations for a variety of medical appointments
  - 1912 January – February (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Of note: reorganization of Graphic Arts, possible appointment of Mr. Har Dayal to teach Indian philosophy, recommendations for Murray S. Wildman
  - 1912 March (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1912 April – May (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Of note: legitimate uses of sabbatical leave, widow's pensions
  - 1912 June - July (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1912 August – September (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Of note: Ernest B. Hoag's possible appointment in Education
  - 1912 October (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Of note: possible elimination of Junior College work (i.e. freshman and sophomore year), letter of J. M. Stillman regarding faculty leave
  - 1912 November – December (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Of note: research leave for faculty, widow's pensions, changing anatomy from a division to a department
  - 1913 January – February (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Of note: anatomy department, letters of recommendation for Gottfried Hult and William H. Carruth
  - 1913 March (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1913 April (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1913 May – June (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1913 July – August (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Of note: recommendations for Victor J. West and John William Davis
  - 1913 September – December (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1914 March – April (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Of note: proposed consolidation of graphic arts with education
  - 1914 May – August (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1914 September – October (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1915 January – March (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Of note: merging of department of English philology with English literature and rhetoric, recommendation for Ralph H. Lutz
  - 1915 April – May (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Of note: recommendations for John S. P. Tatlock
  - 1915 June – July (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Of note: nomination of Dr. Bailey Willis, recommendations for Charles Reining
  - 1915 August – December (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Of note: appointment of Margery Bailey
  - 1916 January – March (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1916 April – August (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Of note: Carnegie pension plan
  - 1916 September – December (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Of note: major department system, reports from department heads about departmental requirements for the A.B. degree
  - 1917 January – February (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1917 March – May (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Of note: plan for the organization of the School of Education
  - 1917 June – August (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1917 September – December (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1918 January – March (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1918 April – May (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1918 June – August (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1918 September – December (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1919 January – February (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 1919 March (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Of note: reports on the amalgamation of the departments of history, economics and political science and the creation of a School of Public Affairs, memoranda on political science by Victor J. West
  - 1919 April – May (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Of note: memoranda on creating School of Public Affairs, recommendations for Reginald G. Trotter
  - 1919 June – August (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1919 September – December (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1920 January – February (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Of note: possibility of limiting instructors to 5 years of service, sabbatical leave, question of intramural golf and tennis on Sundays
  - 1920 March (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1920 April – June (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1920 July – December (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1921 January (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Of note: Report of the Sub-Committee of Advisory Board on Sabbatical Leave
  - 1921 February – April (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1921 May – July (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1921 September – December (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1922 January – February (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Of note: creation of the Department of Classical Literature, report on establishment of School of Biology
  - 1922 March – August (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - 1922 September – December (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - 1923 January (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - 1923 February – April (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - 1923 May – December (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - 1924 January – February (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1924 March – May (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1924 June – December (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1925 January (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1925 March (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1925 April – June (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1925 September – December (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1926 January – March (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 1926 April – May (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Of note: proposal for granting honorary degrees
  - 1926 June – December (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 1927 January – February (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - 1927 March – April (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - 1927 May – August (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 1927 September – December (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - 1928 January – February (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1928 March (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1928 April – May (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1928 June – August (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Of note: photos of Albert Haertlein with letter of recommendation
  - 1928 September – December (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Of note: letters of recommendation for C. B. van Niel and Eugene L. Grant (includes photo of Grant)
  - 1929 January – February (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1929 March – May (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1929 June – August (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1929 October – December (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 1930 January – March (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 1930 April – May (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 1930 June – August (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - 1930 September – December (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - 1931 January – February (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1931 March (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Of note: H. F. Blichfeldt's letter re Henry Lanz; letters of recommendation for Henry Lang (Slavic languages) and James V. Uspensky (mathematics)
  - 1931 April – May (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Of note: proposed articles of organization of the faculty of the school of medicine
  - 1931 June – August (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Of note: letters of recommendation for Hugh Hildreth Skilling
  - 1931 September – December (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1932 January – February (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1932 March (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Of note: H. F. Blichfeldt's endorsement of James V. Uspensky; annotated list of clinical appointments for the school of medicine; M. R. Kirkwood's proposal for changes in law degrees; letters of recommendation for Victor C. Twitty and Richard T. LaPiere
  - 1932 April – May (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Of note: letters and proposal re authorizing a Bachelor of Arts degree in hygiene and physical education
  - 1932 June – August (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - 1932 September – December (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - 1933 January – February (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - 1933 March (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - 1933 April – June (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Of note: recommendations for West lecturers
  - 1933 July – December (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - 1934 January – February (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Of note: letters of recommendation for Bayard Quincy Morgan, Chilton R. Bush,
  - 1934 March (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1934 April – June (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1934 July – December (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Of note: letter of recommendation for Paul R. Hanna with bibliography
  - 1935 January – March (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Of note: letters re C. B. van Niel, record of work of James Percy Baumberger
  - 1935 April – May (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Of note: memo re appointment of consulting professors in the GSB
  - 1934/35 Miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 1935 June – August (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Of note: career summaries for Profs. David Harris and Max Savelle (history dept.)
  - 1935 September – December (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - 1936 January – February (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Of note: letters and c.v. for Stephen Timoshenko, letters of recommendation for George S. Myers (Natural History Museum)
  - 1936 March – April (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - 1936 May – June (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Of note: letters re Victor C. Twitty
  - 1936 September – December (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Of note: letters of recommendation for I. James Quillen
  - 1937 January – February (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Of note: letters of recommendation for John Reid (philosophy)
  - 1937 March (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Of note: recommendations and c.v.'s for F. E. Terman, Rolf. L. Bolin, Robert T. Ross, P. A. Leighton, P. J. van Rysselberghe
  - 1937 April – May (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Of note: recommendations for Karl Spangenberg
  - 1937 September – December (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Of note: recommendations and bibliographies for P. A. Leighton, George S. Parks, Alvin C. Eurich
  - 1938 January – February (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1938 March (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 1938 April – May (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - 1938 October – 1939 June (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 1939 October – 1940 June (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - 1940 October – 1941 June (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1941 October – 1942 August (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 1942 September – 1943 May (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 1943 September – December (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 1944 January – August (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 1944 September – 1945 March (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 1945 April – July (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 1945 September – December (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 1946 January – May (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - 1946 June – August (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1946 September – 1947 February (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1947 March – July (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1947 September – 1948 February (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1948 March – July (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 1966/1967 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 1967/1968 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 1968/1969 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - 1969/1970 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - 1970/1971 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - 1951-1975 Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 11)